He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him.
And they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
time many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show focused on
Enchantment in creation the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers,
but not vampire hunters.
We talked about that.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D. Young,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana,
Kejan Country.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Daymakin,
and Mayas Pennsylvania on the very edge of Pennsylvania Dutch land.
And if you're listening to us live,
You can call in at 8558
radio 855-237-2346.
Matzka Trudy is taking your calls tonight and it is her birthday.
So if you call, you had better wish Matzka Trudy a happy birthday.
I will have her write down the names of those who did not.
Also if you call in speak quietly, I'm still recovering from Marty Grun.
Oh, well, you do live in Louisiana.
Yes.
Yeah.
So please call.
Scott, we'll get to your calls in the second part of the show.
Lotus Spirits is brought to you by our listeners and also by Chrysostom Academy.
A lot of you listeners out there work from home and if you're telecommuting you
can probably live almost anywhere. If you're a parent of school-age kids and
you're like me working from a virtual office. One of your big considerations for
where you live is where your kids go to school. I love living in the Lehigh Valley
of Pennsylvania and part of why is because my kids go to Chrysostom Academy. I'm not
I'm kidding.
It's true.
And it's a Pan Orthodox Classical School with elementary through high school students.
It's on a beautiful 55 acre campus, has the highest academic standards.
It's focused not just on educating the mind but forming the whole person in Christ.
So if you don't live here yet, think about moving to the Lehigh Valley and sending your kids
to Chrysostom Academy.
And even if you don't tell a commute, our local economy is growing.
actual
jobs here. And we've got eight orthodox piercises in our metro area. So you can visit
Crisostomacademy.org. Again, that's Crisostomacademy.org to see what I'm talking about.
You get a legion of people to head over there and make peeps. That's true. They make peeps
not too far from where Crisostomacademy is located. There you go. Your children will learn
you will actually true. Actually, true. Also, Dwayne the Rock Johnson is from Crisostomacademy.
from Chris Astrocategory.
I mean, that's a claim you can't back up.
I know, I know.
I think he went to Liberty High School, maybe.
I'm not sure, which I'm not advertising that.
Yeah, the only really big drawback
if you come here and send your kids to school
is that in some level, on some level,
you have me as your neighbor.
So, sorry.
I'm sorry.
I've successfully disrupted everything.
Go ahead.
Wendy.
But yes.
My wife and I love having our kids there.
It's great.
It's really fantastic.
We're so glad, so glad is there.
Also, so one more, one more little ad.
We're still selling tickets for our Lord of Spirits Conference on October 26th through 29th,
2023. Right now, only commuter tickets are available.
That means you got to get your own hotel room or some place to stay or be in B whatever.
Because y'all have sold out the lodging at the Antioch in Village, you maniacs.
You can still go to store.enchantfaith.com slash events to get your ticket.
And there are actually not even that many...
ticket's left. It's pretty, pretty not. They say that Mr. Durdon is building an army.
Well, the first rule of Lord of Spirits Club, wait,
though you can't talk about the good thing. That's right. That's right. Tonight, tonight,
we continue our conversations on the sacraments of the Church. And we're talking about the holy
mystery of Anction, which can be slippery to get our minds around. What does it do? Why don't we see
miracles every time it's applied is.
is sin related and so on.
So where are we going to start this time, Father Stephen?
Should we just go ahead and start with Genesis?
I think somewhere someone has probably mapped out
the broad structure of a Lord of Spirits episode.
Right.
There's just a generic Lord of Spirits episode out there
that anyone can do at home now.
Actual topic in the third half, right?
Starting somewhere, the murky depths of prehistory.
We're here.
way through. I did want to comment before we get started on a more serious note on the
passing of Dr. Michael Heiser. Which I wanted to comment on for a number of reasons. A lot
of our audience is very familiar with his work. Some people have gone from reading his work
to becoming part of our audience and other folks vice versa.
And because we don't, other than friend of the show,
Bart Irman, we don't comment on a lot of people.
On the show, occasionally we get why don't we talk about him.
People hypothesizing various theories as to why we don't
talk about him and this and that.
And so with his passing earlier this week,
I wanted to kind of...
clarify things regarding that and say a few words.
As I mentioned, I at least don't like talking other than
friend of the show barterman. I don't like talking about people.
I have as a general policy to be ruthless with ideas and
compassionate with people. So when you don't talk about people,
you just talk about ideas. It looks a lot less like a personal
attack and more like just critique and give and take.
working out ideas.
Century Germans, though, are fair game.
Yeah, yeah.
But even then, I rarely named them.
That's true.
So, and Dr. Heiser was a firm believer
in the peer review process.
One of the things, obviously, I didn't know him personally.
As far as I know, he didn't know I existed, right?
But...
beyond pretty much anyone else I've encountered right in academia and
scholarship right he thoroughly believed in the peer review process in
give and take in in hashing things out in that way in the community of scholars
he literally on his deathbed had new issues of journals on his nightstand in
in case he wanted to read.
Hmm.
That's how dedicated...
he was to to scholarship and I have never and never plan on saying anything
negative about his published peer reviewed scholarly work on the Old Testament
which is top notch. Obviously in terms of some of the popular stuff he was an
evangelical. I'm an Orthodox priest so we're coming at things from different
perspectives and we're integrating the scholarly data in different ways in our
viewpoints.
There were times back in the day when I was still in the dark realm of social media where I know
it probably so people remember I publicly disagreed with them about some things, but again
that was part of this give and take, right? When
despite my policy of not wanting on this show to get into personalities and stuff,
when...
A scholar looks at another scholar's work and takes it seriously in things that's important
enough to try to critique it.
That's actually a compliment.
That means that you have a very high impression of that person.
When someone publishes garbage, you don't bother to respond to it.
When someone publishes something important or puts something out there that's important,
that's where you step in in your critique.
So mainly...
I wanted to make that plane because I didn't want anymore rumors and weirdness about things.
And on the whole, I want to say memory eternal to serve God Michael to part of this life,
and that my prayers at least will continue to be with his family, and with him since I'm Orthodox.
But, uh, yeah, just want to
wanted to say that, I didn't want to sort of pass that over in silence with his passing
this week.
So now we have to figure out how to get out of that mood and into our topic for tonight.
So it needs more giggling.
Yeah, exactly.
More will just recitations of the word right.
Right?
Yeah, right?
Right.
Back to Genesis.
Yeah, yeah.
So we are indeed beginning at the beginning,
which is a very good place to start.
And so tonight we're talking about, as you mentioned,
the mystery of Holy Unction,
also known as the anointing of the sick,
which is practice in the Orthodox Church
and some Orthodox churches, as mine,
It is administered to everyone.
on Holy Wednesday, we're at another time in Holy Week,
and is also administered to the sec.
That said, the place where we're starting out tonight
may not look like it's directly related to that.
Unless this is your first time listening,
you're used to that by now.
Right?
But the question is, how will they get there?
Yes, yes.
Yeah, well, you know, actually,
I don't know, contact me.
recently and say, could you guys just like release the bits you do at the end, like as
a separate like clip show, whatever? And it's like, you know, I get what you're saying.
I get what you're saying. But the reason why that stuff at the end is meaningful is because
of the road that we walked to get the journey, not the destination. Yeah, man. It's the
friends we made along the way. Yeah, there we go. There I go being a surfer boy again.
So yeah, so where the place where we're starting is essentially who are you?
Indeed. Who?
Who?
I really want to know.
Anyway.
And who are you meaning?
What is what is a human person?
What is the soul?
What is a body?
How do they relate to each other?
And so to get into that of course
we have to go back to Genesis. We have to go to Genesis chapter two,
Genesis chapter two, verse seven, to the creation of Adam,
the creation of the creation of man.
Yeah, and this is a passage we've talked about before in other contexts.
That's the cool stuff. That's one of the cool things about, especially the beginning of Genesis, is you can
talk about these chapters from a gazillion different angles and they're all very fruitful.
not to mix my metaphors too much.
Yes. So Genesis chapter 2, verse 7, then the Lord God forms the man of dust from the ground and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life and the man became a living creature or sometimes it's translated he became a living soul, right? A living soul.
Yes. Yeah.
And this, of course, gets quoted later by St. Paul in 1 Corinthians 1545, when he compares
that
to the relationship between Christ and the Spirit who gives life, but that's a
rabbit trail we won't go down this evening because that's one of the trickiest
verses in the Bible to translate. I mean, you're the rabbit though so I'm just
throwing that out there. Don't know what to do with that. It's our year man. That's
what all the Chinese people tell me is that because it's the year the rabbit.
This is our year. Okay, okay. I'm just saying okay
Yes.
So what is the soul fight?
You say you want me to go for it?
No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Okay.
I was just growing that out.
I mean, I could.
On some future episode where we're feeling like we need to go for four hours.
Okay.
So what do we see here?
Right?
So he becomes a living being, a living soul, right?
When the breath of life is breathed into him.
Right.
And so I'll just say early.
on, sorry, plateness, you're really going to take it on the chin for this one.
So, the soul here is not a thing.
It's not a glowing orb that rises out of your chest when you die.
It's not shaped in any way, yeah, or a green mist that Shang Tsung eats.
No.
It's not a thing.
It's not an object, right?
you have Adam's body is formed, right?
And then...
And that form, that body is given life.
And so Nefish and Hebrew, right,
Seeky and Greek, is a way of referring to that life,
the life of the living thing.
And so as we mentioned before on the show,
everything that's alive has a soul.
Right.
If you are animate.
Yeah, if you're animate, you have a soul.
pun intended for you Latin speak.
Animate, an animate literally means sold and soulless.
In Latin.
So, but there are different types of souls, right?
So, yes, animals have souls.
No, those are different than human souls, right?
They're not identical.
Your dog has a dog soul.
Yes.
And your tree has a tree soul.
So what that reveal?
When we talk about the type of soul, the type of life that is in a particular type of body,
and particular type of body is exactly the kind of language that St. Paul uses in 1 Corinthians 15
to talk about animals and people.
The type of life that's in that particular type of body is directly related to that body.
You can just trade out souls.
right they can't like
migrate back and forth between ghosts in the show and and cats and a human or
Freaky Friday. So that's two humans but we'll get there. That's true. That's true.
So this shows that that life, right, the life of that body, being a particular
type of life, also reveals that the soul that life is an organizing principle of
of that by
Right, and often when that's being discussed, the word spirit gets used because, you know,
see the spirits episode, right, where we talk about spirit as being the kind of, as the animating
force, the organizing principle, the thing that's pulling everything and making it go, so to speak,
I don't want to use a puppet metaphor too much, but you know what I mean? Yeah, you know, you could,
you could so you could groom a wolf to look like a German shepherd. Right?
But if it still be a wolf, not a dog, part because it has wolf soul, not dog soul.
Right.
And when it comes over, it's not like a dog.
So the type of life, the type of soul that is in the body, organizes the body.
And if you stop grooming that wolf, it would go back to looking like a wolf.
And the acorn will always grow into an oak tree.
It will never grow into a fig tree.
Because what it is is already there in the life that it has, even as the body changes.
I have each of those in my yard.
The acorns that the oak tree gives off never become fig trees.
So I've done this with science.
It can verify.
Yes, buddy.
such cases. And so this is why, right? So sometimes we've we've brushed over this before in previous
episodes. Sometimes there are places arguably in the scriptures, definitely in the church fathers,
where the soul and the spirit are or are not distinguished from.
each other. Yeah, I mean in patricity, you get both you know human beings are body and soul
and then also you get human beings are body soul and spirit. Yes, or even body and spirit once
a while. But so what's what's going on there? And so I think we've at least once had a caller
ask us that question like which is it right? And so the what we have to remember here is that
just because you make a distinction in speech that doesn't mean there's a
actual distinction. Right. So, you know, you will see things like with the church
fathers are talking about the Trinity and they'll talk about like a ray of the
Sun and its warmth and its light. Right. Like you can talk about those things
separately. You can talk about the warmth of the Sun and the light of the Sun.
Right. But in reality, those are not really two separate things. Right.
Thank you.
Right, so but you're able to distinguish those in speech and so sometimes
Right
The the fathers when they separate soul and spirit as two different things
They're making that kind of distinction that doesn't mean that they're actually two separate things because neither of those is a
Thing in the sense that we think about material objects, right? Yeah
and and when that distinction is made it's a distinction between just the life
of something and life as that organizing principle. Yeah. So if you go back to our
episode on what is a spirit when it's at home, right? We talk about how a
spirit is sort of an organizing principle like a higher level of collective
consciousness, right? And so that organizing principle
aspect is what they're calling spirit when they separate the two.
Yeah.
And the soul is referring to just the life of the thing itself, right?
But you don't have to distinguish those.
Right.
And I mean, it's, it's maybe analogous, but not identical to, you know, I'm me,
but then I'm also a father, but I and my being a father are new, not two
different things, you know, I'm still me when I'm acting in a fatherly way.
but that's...
know, we can talk about, we can talk about it, but it's still me the whole time.
It's still husband.
You father, you son, you are not different use.
Right.
Exactly.
That are partitioned from each other, but you can speak, we can speak about them separately.
Right.
Yeah.
So that's, that's kind of what's actually going on with a soul.
So you can't picture a soul.
Right.
It doesn't look like anything.
is the life of a body.
Right. So when we're if you've seen someone or something die, what we're identifying,
what's called a soul is the difference between the thing when it was alive and the thing
when it's dead. The thing that's gone, which is not a material thing. Right. Well,
It's a little talk a little bit more about why it's hard to talk about.
that. Right. Yeah. But so what tends to happen, especially in languages like Latin and English,
both of them have a bad tendency to do this. This is why Heiderger said you can only do philosophy
in Greek and German. Not because he was at all. Yeah. Well, you know, he was a native German speaker
in his Greek is better than his Latin. So, you know, there might have been some influence there. But
Um, yeah, but
English and Latin tend to reify things.
Right. It's just the way that it tends to work.
Yeah.
And with English, we've got articles to make it even more.
People were possible.
Right.
This causes all kinds of theological problems, if you're not careful.
Right. So people all the time in English will talk about Christ's human nature and His divine nature.
Yeah. As though they're like separate things where he's making it.
make a few lectures.
Yeah, doing this. Like there are two things and that's the story of that's bad, right?
Or talking about A soul as if it's a thing.
Right in this particular case. And that language is deceptive and plays into some bad conclusions
like the ones come to by Plato and John Calvin.
Yeah, there's gonna be a whole lot of sorry play to it.
I'm sorry Calvin and even some sorry origin.
Yes.
That's part of the podcast.
We're going to be apologizing a lot.
There's a lot of sorry's.
A lot of sorry's.
The South Pole.
So it works.
And the reason I wrote in Jean Calving is that he famously
to the chagrin to be fair of many Calvinists.
But he quoted is true Plato's statement that the body is the
the prison house of the soul.
Oh, John, not his best moment by anyone's standards.
So he, you know, by doing that was buying into a lot of bad presuppositions, because of
course for Plato, the soul is the self.
Yeah, it's who you are.
Right, you are your soul.
which is in a body. Right. Like it's a big mech. Yeah. You're inside.
That's all in some numbers.
Embodied, but that's not a particularly good thing. In fact, it's kind of a bad thing.
Yeah, right. Right. And that's why it's a prison house. Right.
And the goal is to get out. Right. And so there are a number of things in
and played out that flow from this.
and that have been sort of wholesale adopted in Western thought.
Like, the idea that the soul is immortal.
And by that, we don't mean that we think souls vanish and disappear or something at some
point, but the idea that the soul is innately immortal.
Yeah, it's not able to be destroyed or to die.
Yeah, it's not able to die.
Right.
And there are extreme forms of that when you veer into
Anastasism right where it's some spark of it's some element of God himself right like
Some element of the divine essence in each person or something right, but there's less extreme versions which is just that the soul is is
Is immortal in and of itself right not related to yeah, it's it at least all kinds of other conclusions like that they pre-exist this human life
You know, right there immortal and go on forever
Yeah, looking at you, Origin, looking at you, Mormons.
Um, you know, uh, well, to be fair to the Mormons, the Mormons did think they came into
being at a point.
That's true.
Yeah.
Sorry, Mormons.
So it's a little different.
They do believe they pre-exist embodiment, but not the way Plato and Origin.
Yeah.
We do have some Mormon listeners, actually.
So, yeah, Mormons.
Yeah.
So we, yeah.
Um, but.
so that
Those are more or less unsuttle ways of doing the pre-existence of the human soul.
There are more subtle ways.
So for example, one of the more subtle ways would be again, in Calvinism, where the human
soul essentially pre-exist in the divine decree.
Yeah, it's in the mind of God, and so therefore it has an existence.
the divine decree.
in the eternal mind of God, not only just sort of a general sense of a person is going to
come to exist.
Not just like God knows what's going to happen, but that person's actual character, every
action they're going to take in their life, everything they're going to do, whether they're
elect and going to go to heaven or reprobate and going to go to the bad place.
All of that is reality.
before
They come into being
Right and so this is a more subtle way to do that
Which is which is not ultimately less
Less problematic right and because what it leads to in any of those cases
And this is why I'm bringing Kalanism into that it's not just a slander it and call them plate slander them and call them plateness
It's because
in any of those cases what you end up with is the, and again, the Mormons, there's some nuance here.
But you end up with human life on this earth just being the playing out of the identity of the soul that already exists.
So essence pre- your essence precedes your existence.
Right, right, and so, you know,
that this actually has a lot of,
I mean, this all sounds very philosophical,
I know metaphysical, or whatever, everybody.
But it actually has some actual practical ways
that this gets played out in the way that people think
of themselves and the way they try to lead their lives
and the way that they do their relationships.
Yes, right?
So we could talk about this.
Yeah.
People who are pregnant, yeah.
And there are male spouses, sorry everybody.
Right, so people will talk about like, I need to find out who I really am.
Yeah.
Well, I was going to say, I can't wait to meet this person.
Oh, right, I can't wait to meet them.
It gets to know who they are, right?
Yeah.
They're a fetus.
They aren't anybody yet.
Yeah.
They're human, but they don't have like a personality.
Right.
They don't have a favorite flavor of ice cream, right?
They don't have a favorite Shakespearean play.
as much as I'm sure you've tried when your wife was pregnant to play Kenneth
Branagh productions sort of at them in utero to get them to pick one. Hey much
to do about nothing is a brilliant piece of modern cinema. Okay I enjoy it
also but come on man at least go for baby Mozart or something. Oh yeah the idea
that these things about
you already exist and they just kind of play themselves out. You just figure them out as you go through life.
Yeah, and you're a good person or a bad person. Right, right. Or even like this plays
with the whole idea of like soulmates, for instance, you know, I'm meant for this one other person
because this is who we are from all eternity or whatever. I actually one of my favorite
non-none little earth things that were ever said by by Jared Tolkien.
is he said, the soulmate is the person you're actually married to.
I love that because it's about the way that things actually are, not living in this virtual reality
about how you think about things, but life as it really is. Yeah, except for me and my wife,
who are like hawk man and hawk woman. Okay, so there's, but yeah, for most people.
So, uh, Montana Guardians. Um, so, um, yeah, it's...
So there's this idea then and it's everywhere.
Right, it's everywhere.
I've got this is who I am.
I need to figure out who I am.
I need to reveal who I am.
I'm confused about who I am, right?
This is just who I am, which is a way of saying
I can't and won't repent.
Yeah.
So this has actual consequences this view, right?
of the person being the soul, the soul.
already existing and being immortal and then it just finding itself in a body.
Yeah. So there are consequences of this. When we jettison that view, that platonic view,
and get down to no, the soul is just the life that is in your body, right? That is animating it, right?
And one of them is, and I know you loved this phrase when I
I told it to you earlier, if you weren't you, you wouldn't be you.
It's very similar to one of my other favorite phrases,
wherever you go, there you are.
But here's what this means.
This goes beyond you don't know what it's like to be a bat.
This is the next level, everybody.
So write this down.
The next level of baddiness.
And cosplay is if you weren't you, you wouldn't be you.
How do you cosplay that?
I don't know, creativity.
So what that means is, we think it'd be fantasized.
And we were like, what if I had been born in 16th century France?
But what if I had been born in the Roman Empire?
What if I had been born in pick, 19th century Russia?
We fantasize we think about it, but but here's here's the sad truth. You're doing the same thing is imagining what it would be like if you were a bat
Yeah, or as you're assuming freaky, right? Yeah, you're assuming that your formed identity would just be sort of taken out of your current self would be deposited in some body
in that place and time
Which isn't how that works?
Right, human beings are more permeable.
That's why I get I'm trying to start with a Spanish word permeable.
You know, you're not exclusively a product of your environment or whatever, but you're
not a product of your environment.
Right.
So, if you, if quote unquote you had been born in 16th century France, that would be a
different person.
Yeah, and you'd be much more like the other 16th century French people.
Yes, there is no way in which that person would be you.
Hmm.
There's not.
Even if you find a photo of someone from a couple centuries ago that looks like you,
that's still not you.
It could be time traveling.
It could be time traveling you from the future.
It could be that Nicholas Cage is a vampire.
But probably, you know, in general cases, it's not you, right?
And this means that what we're getting at here...
is that actually your body is more related to your identity than your soul is.
Hmm.
You have to unpack that one because I'm afraid we're going to go,
what?
What?
Human souls are more like each other than human bodies are.
Yeah, because it's the life of the body.
Like the, the genitive is, yeah, it goes the world.
It's just human life force.
Right.
it's human life that is in your body.
And so this, if you wanna place,
where this comes out in theological history,
right, this becomes really important,
this idea of the soul becomes really important
in the debates regarding a pollinarianism.
Yeah, and, you know.
Quick review for everybody who hasn't been reading about the early heresy is a
Paulinarianism was teaching and this is the basic version of it that Christ did not have a human soul
instead the logos the word of God functioned as the controlling element of his body.
Basically, right, right. And this was held by ancient people and by certain quasi-Christian
and apologists on the West Coast.
Um, see, I don't name...
people. That's right. Some other guy that uses three names all the time. So yeah, it's
weird. Anyway, your middle name isn't duh. Even duh. Yeah, it's D. My middle name is
D. D. So why is that relevant to this? Well, the perspective from which a pollinarians
are coming.
is essentially a sort of platonic view of what a soul is.
So for them, if the soul is the self,
if the soul is the person, if the soul is the identity,
and you say that Christ had a human soul,
then for them you're saying, well then he was what, two people?
Yeah, right.
Right.
And aforementioned unnamed person.
makes a similar kind of argument.
Yeah, I'm trying to come up with one analogy.
Again, just an analogy, everybody.
That seems to work in my mind is, you know,
you could have a computer with a motherboard, right?
And this is sort of the concept in some ways
of the way we think about human souls and bodies.
You know, the motherboard is a thing
that's really making the computer go,
and if you pull it out, you could put in a different one.
It'll function differently.
But I think souls are more like batteries.
Uh...
Although you can't just switch them out. So that's where the analogy falls to
you know, it's more like the power itself. Yeah. Okay. There you go. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
It's more like the power itself. Yeah. The power. So yeah. You can see how
the uponarians have a problem with that view of the soul. Right. But if you
understand that the soul is just the life of the body. Right. Then of course
Christ had a human soul. He had a human body and human body. He's alive. Right.
Yeah, so yeah, definitely he had
a human soul. Yeah, and human bodies are not animated by anything but human souls. Like
there's not some other way to do it. Which strongly suggests then? I mean, because we can
imagine other ways to do it, right? We have these things in our literature. Apollinarianism
is in fact, theologically, a zombie jamboree. Yes, a dead man's party. Leave your body at the door.
Yeah, so this
this decision here regarding a pulmonary aneurysm.
Again, in addition to the idea that the soul is not the identity
right of the person, right, it's not the self
that it is the life force of the body, right?
This also means there's nothing conflicting, right, because the divine person of the logos is also not a soul.
Hmm.
Right, a soul is a different thing. He's not an identity or a center of consciousness.
Right, the logos, the sun is a divine person who takes upon himself human nature, which
includes a human body, a human soul, right, those things. But there is no sort of extra
self in there somewhere.
or the divine person of the locus is not something that could be slotted into a body.
Right. Right. Right.
So in case I haven't made enough people grumpy at me, right?
This includes biological sex. I'm sorry.
And by that we mean the state of being male or female.
Right. In terms of biological sex.
Yes.
which I should point out by the way and I don't have my jingle geared up here but the word sex itself,
it's etymologically related to words like sex and section, it means difference. It's
it's difference that there is no sex that's literally same sex is it means same different.
Well now you're really just trying to get me. Yeah, I'm just putting that out there.
But yeah, no, it includes it includes what so if you
are an animate human body, right?
If your soul is not some center of the self
or some kind of, Laura, like you aren't other than your body.
Yeah.
You can have feelings and experiences like that
and people do, right?
But that is not because like there's some kind of mismatch,
Right. Right. You can't actually, sorry, need to be born.
out of time. Right? You can't be born in the wrong time.
Because if you were in another time, you wouldn't be you or in or in a wrong
whatever, or in the wrong body. Yeah, you are what you are. Yeah. Yeah.
Cause you wouldn't be you. Right. Right. It would be someone else. Right.
And there are other people in the world.
I've heard that. Yes.
Who are those other people?
you would be had you been born where they are. So that this also means that we as an
animate as a living human body, right? We in that sense, right, we're an object in the world
that other people see an encounter, right, and interact with. So when someone's
sees me like when I walked into the church this evening and a parishioner who I
won't name was was on her way out because she doesn't want to be mentioned on the show.
When she saw me she did not see my soul. I see your soul, Father Stephen. She did not see my inner
identity, my inner self. She did not behold my essence. Right? She saw the living human body in
in the world that is me.
That's what she saw. That's what made various noises and gestures at her that she interpreted
as speech. Right? That's how we relate to and see each other. And this reality, right,
we are living human bodies, right?
Is why relics are a thing, see our relics episode.
Yeah. Because those those pieces are that person. Yes. This is why when the
scriptures talk about what we call the intermediate state, right, or the state of
the soul after physical death, right? This is why everything is so vague and
Nebulous. Yeah, even we've got the language of being hid with Christ your life.
because he'd with Christ.
Yeah, or all the language about sleeping.
Like we don't, we don't,
North-Axerch doesn't teach soul sleep,
but that language is certainly all over the place.
Yeah, right.
Right.
This is why it's so ambiguous and nebulous, right?
Because this is a weird and unnatural thing.
It's not how we were made to be.
Right, human beings were not created to die physically
or spiritually, right?
And so it can't be nailed down.
Yeah.
You go with the plate in this view, and this may be one of the things that makes it attractive to folks.
Right? Then that whole thing makes sense. Right?
If an orb sort of coes out of my chest like negative man and flies up into the into heaven or goes down into the ground.
Right? And we have this image of you know, our shadowy self or force ghost or orb or whatever is floating around in one place or another
and then returns to our body in the resurrection.
I mean, that's still weird, but I mean, it's easier to wrap our head around.
Whereas the language of Scripture, you frankly just, you can't nail it down at all, which
is exactly what you would expect if the other is actually what's true.
Yeah, I mean, we use metaphorical language.
We talk about the soul taking a journey after death.
We use that.
We talk about the soul going into the underworld or the soul going into be with God or into
Abraham's bosom.
But
it's metaphorical language. I mean, it's okay to use it, but we need to understand that
it's not ghosts wandering around, you know. Right. No ectoplasm being left in a trail.
Right. We talked about this on the spirits of the head. And this is why the bodily
resurrection is so concretely important. Yeah. Right. That the, for you to be you,
right for you
to live forever, you have to be back in your body. Otherwise, it wouldn't be you. And so
your identity requires you maintaining your identity requires the bodily resurrection.
This is ultimately why the reincarnation dog don't hunt.
Yeah, because it's not and it's funny because a lot of the reincarnation
doctrines include this I have deive losing your memory of who you were before
Right, which which says that you're not really you
Right, you're not actually that person
Right, you're functioning as a you are the right like it doesn't it wouldn't be the same
Yeah, it doesn't work right. It doesn't work. Yeah, it's not you know, sorry into good girls
It's not how long till my soul gets it right yeah
And you will this is also why that whole uploading your brain to a computer thing will never work
Thank you.
Oh man, actually no thank God.
Right.
Because what will happen is you will die and a computer simulation AI with your memories
will have the experience of waking up inside a computer.
Usually that's the point where there's some kind of disembodied scream.
But that ain't you, you're dead.
It all the same.
Yeah, right, right.
Because yeah.
It's not you.
So um...
Yeah, so a question that might arrive that we might anticipate from this, right?
There's a couple.
One might be, you know, wait, are you now turning around over against the whole theme
of your show and telling us that there is no spiritual element of humanity?
Answer that is of course, no, we already talked about soul spirit.
talked about how the back to the new episode, how human persons interact.
with the spiritual world. There is of course a spiritual element of man, but another one might be
and this is related that you know we keep saying sorry Calvinist, but haven't we kind of smuggled
in a kind of determinism. Right, if the material is the real you, does that mean that you are just
the product of a bunch of chemical reactions and such.
Yeah, cause an effect by a lot.
biological, biological determinism, right?
If I had been born in that family, I'd be that person, right?
And that's true at the start.
Yes, if you had been born in that family,
instead of that person, you would be that person, right?
Right.
Right? Like if, you know, 47 years ago,
I had been born the son of Father Andrew's parents.
I would be him.
That I wouldn't be.
That's gross.
That's a good idea.
Sorry, that's not that.
But, right, that would have happened, right?
Like, and I would be a different person.
But, but, if you've been paying attention to what we've already said,
that doesn't mean that I would have done all the things that Father Andrew did.
Hmm, yeah.
That doesn't mean I would have made all the same decisions.
It doesn't mean I wouldn't-
made all the same choices. Right? Because part of the fact that my life isn't just the
playing out of what I already am, is that I'm then free. Yeah. Right. And the way, for
example, Father Duma True's Stenoloise says this is he talks about this as being one element
of humanity as image
God is that just as God is absolute meaning in determined, undetermined, free. God is not bound by anything.
Sorry, Calvinist with your justice thing. God is not bound by anything. Humans as imagers of God
according to Father Stanley Lloyd, are in some degree, a lesser degree, a lesser degree.
also absolute able to separate themselves from the material system of causation of
cause and effect and make actual choices.
Yeah, and, you know, not to give too much ammunition to that Eugene guy, but, um, I mean,
this is actually part of Tolkien's anthropology in...
Oh, why though?
I know.
I mean, what can I say?
But, I mean, this is something that a lot of people, a lot of people have read, you know.
popular set of books. I guess. I watch the movies once. Not the Lord of the Rings, the Hobbit
ones, the Hobbit ones, my favorite. They really should have just called those the dwarves because
that's what those movies were about. But that is not this podcast. That I'm forbidden love.
Yeah, go ahead.
If I have any goats with me tonight you have them. No, that was the best part of
those movies was that relationship.
Anyway, go out.
Wow.
Is that where I get women hooks up with the dwarf?
Is that how that figured?
Yeah.
So yeah, I'll be talking like the one
the thing that distinguished one of the big things
that distinguished humans from elves in his world
is that there's the music, which is sort of the blueprint
for creation from the very beginning.
And humans have the ability to go outside the music.
Like they can do stuff that's unexpected even to...
the Valar who are sort of the angelic beings in Tolkien's world, whereas elves can't do that.
And it's why humans have this sort of redemptive capability that no one else does.
It's interesting how deeply Christian all that stuff is, how about that?
But yeah, it's interesting that he messes around a lot with the whole idea of Frate and Freewill
and one of the constants in is that humans, even though they're not omnipotent.
You know, they're not universally capable.
They do have free will.
They can actually do unexpected things.
Things that are unexpected, not to God,
but to pretty much everything else in the whole creation.
So yeah.
And that's true.
That's for real.
So all right, well, we're gonna go ahead
and take our first break and we'll be back in a moment
with the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment.
Take your calls.
the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
What is the spiritual significance of Almsgiving? In the new booklet, spiritual transformation and
giving. Bishop Alexi of Sietka, and Alaska, draws from a wealth of
of patric and modern sources.
to explore why God commands us to give.
What motivates people to give or hold back?
What spirit should characterize our giving
and the result of spiritual transformation
that occurs in our heart when we give?
Find spiritual transformation and giving
at store.enginefaith.com
That's store.enginefaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits.
The father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back.
Give us a ring at 855-AF radio.
You know with all this, this who question
where we keep asking, there's two things I wanted to mention.
Number one, during my stage in the day,
is I actually worked at the WHO concert.
So I think was...
like 1997, maybe, which is before some of y'all were even born.
And although their drummer was Zach Starky,
the son of Ringo Star.
The other thing I want to mention is that
the very first line in Hamlet,
since I already mentioned Shakespeare,
very first line in Hamlet is, who's there?
Who's there?
And when I took a Hamlet course as an undergrad,
we spent three and a half weeks on who's there.
Which every time I say that in the presence of my wife,
she'll be like, oh.
But it was one of the...
best three and a half weeks that I've ever had in my educational experience. So I'm just throwing that out there for all the English lit nerds.
Who's there?
You don't have anything to say to that father?
Or maybe he stepped out. It's all mine.
Here we are, Lord of Spirits, just Father Andrew Stephen Damick.
No Father Stephen the Young. What could happen? We don't know.
all kinds of things that could happen.
So...
Things are happening.
Yes.
He's back.
I was at living and you didn't hear the brilliance
and I just throughout it everybody.
I need to run longer commercials.
I know.
We'll have a talk with Trudy about that.
Happy birthday, Trudy.
There's gonna be something we can advertise for Pete's sake.
I know.
Yes.
I was just mentioning I once spent three and a half weeks.
studying the first line of Hamlet, which is who's there.
Very, very relevant to all these questions we've been asking about who and the who.
So was that a stunt?
No, not at all.
Talking Shakespeare now.
See, that's the other thing.
That's the other thing.
One of the other things I'm nerdy about that people actually don't generally know
if they listen to my podcast that I'm a super big Shakespeare fan.
Yes.
Something rotten in Denmark.
Podcast for Mankshit Faith Ministries.
Hey man.
The Poisoned Chalice.
Yeah.
When you ever get tired of that rolling guy.
It's an idea.
Show him a side and go Shakespeare.
That's right.
No more medieval.
We're doing run in Sunsnow boys.
Yeah.
Okay, welcome back anyway.
It's the second half.
We just got through doing a whole 48 minutes of sorry Calvinist, sorry Plato, sorry origin.
Sorry, I'm in the middle of this place.
Play-Doh. Yeah, a little bit more play-Doh brain. I'd feel as him as lame.
We play-Doh brain. Play-Doh some kind of wide-eyed idealist or
He's idealist in the true sense the original I have an idea of play-Doh
Maybe still the best
This is where those parts where we're just like riffing and there are people out there like typing angry
reviews and comments about this show could be 50 per
100 shorter if you cut out all the giggling all of these things right all the nonsense all the nonsense
That other people will reply and say but we're here for the nonsense. We love the nonsense. We're here for it
Yeah, so okay, but enough now we're actually now we're actually moving into we're getting closer now
Towards hot sense. Oh to our topic. Yeah a little bit closer. Yeah healing
So healing yes our second half
Right so
We've talked now about what a human person is. Now we're going to get into what it means
for a human person to find healing. And so, of course, the concept of healing is found
throughout the scriptures.
Yeah, kind of everywhere. But there are, I think, two significant phases that we can identify
in terms of how healing is talked about in the scripture.
One being an early phase in ancient Israel, the other coming later in Israelite history and then flowing into the New Testament.
And this is not a change in the sense that there was sort of one view, and that was abandoned in place of another view.
No, it's just a question of perspective.
Right.
Looking at the same, you know, like one is kind of from 50,000 feet and the other is kind of zoomed in.
right and keeping
both as we're going to see when we get to the end of this half, I make a promise to you,
dear listener, keeping them both together is going to be important. The way that the two
connect to each other is going to be important. So we'll start with that sort of first phase,
the ancient Israelite phase, and we're starting in the Torah really with this phase.
and the way in which illness sickness
Right, ill health, lack of health is talked about in this early phase is in terms of plague.
Yes, so mass, bad health.
Yes, so waves of pestilence or plague coming upon populations and spreading.
And one of the earliest places we see that is actually in the form of a sign that's given to Moses.
God before he is sent to speak to Pharaoh, to demand that Pharaoh let the Israelites go.
Yeah, this is one of the weirdest things, a weird, weird thing.
So we don't have to talk about the staff turning into a snake and any of the other snakes
because everybody listened to the Battle Wizard's episode.
That was a cool episode.
And so they know that that was a traditional ancient Near Eastern Wizard duel.
the other sign that Moses is given where he puts his hand
to do his coat and pulls it out and it's leprous, right? It's infected with a plague. And then he
puts it back in the coat and pulls it out and it's healed. And so what is this one about?
Right? Well, I mean, it's a cool trick, but I mean, yeah, that's not why God gives signs.
Right. Yeah, like if you're going to come up with some spectacular thing to show you're a powerful
source for like this is not the one.
that you would yak. Yeah. I mean, you didn't have Moses go and pull a quarter out for behind Pharaoh's
ear, right? Like this isn't just tricks, right? This is to show not just the power of God, but
something specific about the power of God. Because of course, the purpose of these signs, even though
God not only knew they weren't going to work, but told Moses they weren't going to work before he
You did the perfero.
Yeah, you're going to work this, but it's not going to work, but go do it.
Is that Pharaoh had no reason to respect the God of a bunch of slaves?
Right, because not only he's out of his pride or whatever, but also think about this,
if you remember the Spirit's ideas, they're a bunch of slaves, so how great can their
controlling Spirit really be?
Right.
the best he can do for them.
mind, right? Mine are clearly better because I haven't
enslaved you. Right. My God can power me and your God's, your
God is really not great. Right. And so this is showing the
power of God, but showing a specific power of God that God
has control over plague. Right. Which is God has control over
plague. You know, and so it's of course plague the ancient
world. And that's tough. There was a leg of legs. Yeah, I mean,
It's it's it's it's it's it's uncle
controllable, it's, you know, everybody feels helpless. It's the worst. It's really, really, but I mean we all know what that's like right now. And this was well through history. Right. Yeah. I mean, we had a pandemic, but
I know a lot of people died, but sorry folks compared to like the black plague. Yeah, where it's like it was not a black plague. One third, I think of the population dies in the
Europe. Yeah. Europe. Yeah. That's a lot. Right. And so what is this? What is this vision
of what disease, what ill health, what plague, what pestilence is. Well, it's this force out there
in the world. Is this force that's out there active in the world that can come and visit destruction
upon you, or that maybe there might be some way to ward it off, to either stop a plague once it
starts or to ward it off and keep plague from befalling you and go befall someone else instead.
Yeah, right.
And this force out there in the world had a name in the ancient Near East.
This demonic force of pestilence was called Reshif, or some very close variation with those
consonants in the ancient world.
And when I say in the ancient Near East, in the ancient world, I mean pretty much everywhere
at over a long period of time.
Yeah, long period of time.
So that...
The earliest inscriptions we have about Rachev are in Syria and from the third millennium
BC.
So the 2000s BC.
Right.
So that's 4,000 years ago.
Yes.
Roughly.
More like 4,500, frankly.
4,500.
4,500 years ago.
And then we have mentions in Ugarit in Syria, in Anatolia, meaning Turkey, like the Hittites.
Uh
South Central, what's now Turkey, Egypt, the Egyptians assimilate Reshift, which is very
rare for them to assimilate Seminit God from outside.
The Carthaginians have, Reshift will tell you a little detail about that in a minute,
the way up to Cicero in the first century BC.
mentions the Phoenician Apollo,
who he calls Apollo Arsipus.
If you look at the consonants of Arsipus,
it's Reshif.
Right, you got the Ruh,
and the...
Right, and there are depictions of Apollo
that match depictions of Reshif.
Yeah, so we're talking basically...
2500, 3000 years of...
B-
leaf in this demonic presence.
Right. Which, I mean, again,
plagues are a big deal, big, big deal in the ancient world.
They rock everybody's world in a really awful way.
To give you an idea of how prominent he was
throughout this period, there's a treaty
between Philip of Macedon, who you might know
as Alexander the Great's dad,
and Hannibal of Carthage
the elephant guy in the fourth century BC and in that one of the gods invoked
from the Carthaginian side is Reshaf. That's not nice. It's a way of, right? The
idea is if I violate this treaty may plague, right? Yeah, a curse. Yeah, like a big
curse come upon me. Right. Because these these treaties these
please come in and have a blast.
and cursus, right?
Kind of like Deuteronomy.
So, how is Reshift depicted?
Reshift is always depicted as an archer.
This is common across all these cultures.
And he has these arrows that are often depicted
as kind of fiery burning arrows,
but the burning is aimed at the idea of infection.
Someone who has an infection has it runs a fever.
Yeah, right.
Their body becomes hot.
And so the image of Reshif as this force behind Pleg is that he comes to an area, he launches his arrows into the population.
They hit indiscriminately, the way the Pleg does.
And strike people down.
So when we say he's worshiped and stuff, he's invoked, it's a curse there.
And the worship is more sort of the warding off.
Right? We keep him happy, we ward him off, we keep him at a distance.
Maybe try to get them to go after our enemies if it'll help us.
Right?
And so there are a lot of places in the Old Testament and the scriptures as a whole where
this imagery shows up.
And we're not going to go through all of them.
We went through a little bit of Reshift stuff in another previous episode.
And I know we talked about at least the Joe passage that we're not going to talk about
tonight there.
about a few passages that either directly mentioned Reshif or a loo-
to him in the Old Testament to make a particular point.
Yeah. And about, yeah. Part of the reality, of course, is that as we're all reading
translations of the Bible, we're often what happens is these names get translated according
to what the name means. Like it would be like, for instance, if, you know, if you're
transiting the New Testament, you come across the apostle, I'm named after instead of saying,
know. And Andrew brought, you know, the boy with the five loaves and the two fish.
It says, and the manly one brought, you know, like that would be what's going on there.
Yeah. And it's deliberate in a lot of cases. Yeah.
Modern translations. It's trying to demythologize the text.
Yeah. And admittedly, these names mean this thing that the God is associated with.
But there's a reason for that. You know, it's all kind of bound up as one image.
you know so yeah so the first example.
as Deuteronomy chapter 32, verses 23 and 24.
And I will heap disasters upon them.
I will spend my arrows on them.
They should be wasted with hunger
and devoured by Reshif and Ketav.
I will send the teeth of beasts against them
with the venom of things that crawl in the dust.
And Reshif there, like if you were looking at the ESV,
it'll say devoured by plague.
and then KETA of Poisonist Pestilance.
So that's why you don't see Reshev and Ketev probably if you pull your Bible off the shelf and look at Deuteronomy 30.
Dependent.
But yeah, I mean, maybe.
Who knows?
But we should also mention here Ketev and there's also a Deber who are other sort of demonic forces associated with disease and pestilence.
Yeah.
Who get paired a lot, as you'll see in some of these with Reshev.
Yeah, so there's another one, Psalm 78, 48, and this is the Psalm.
so as much later after this happens, but it's talking about the play.
sent on Egypt. He gave over their cattle to the hail and their flocks to Reshefts, which,
so in the ESV, they get translated as thunderbolts, so a little bit less of a literal translation.
But again, it's like that God threw Reshefts at them.
Right. Yeah. They're flags on Egypt, right? God is kind of unleashing
these forces on them.
Yep. Okay, so another one is Habakkuk chapter three verses three through five.
Habakkuk being everyone's favorite book of the Bible.
Of a womb as it were. There's there's cool stuff in there. Oh yeah. Yeah. Under under red.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay, so verse three, God came from Teeman and the Holy One from Mount Paran.
His splendor covered the heavens and the earth was full of his praise. His brightness was like the
light raise flash from his hand and there
he veiled his power before him went deber and rechef followed at his heels.
We just heard verses three and four a bunch of times in church by the way.
Paying close attention. But notice in the last verse and verse five,
right? So it's talking about sort of God in his majesty like processing, right?
And before him goes Debra, after him is...
so they're like, Petsy has an aliche. Right? Right. Their forces that are under his control.
And this is, let's say we saw that kind of thing before with Leviathan, the idea that Leviathan
is, even despite being this primordial massive underwater sea serpent is also like his cat that he
sort of planes with. Right. Right. And and so in these quotes you see.
that it's not denying that this force exists out in the world, right? But it's
placing this force under the control of Yahweh, the God of Israel, right?
That's the whole hand in the coat thing. Yeah. And as we've said before on the
show, this is a major element of the Odyssey and the Old Testament in the Hebrew
Bible is that God is in control of these things, even these things which are
You
evils and he uses them to his ends to bring good out of them.
And so since he has control of them, you can have an exorcism prayer like Psalm 91 or 90 in the
Greek numbering, which was is the first of the Davidic exorcism prayers found at Kumran is also
in the book of Psalms and our Bibles.
Yeah, well, and isn't that verse, isn't that some used in the Orthodox funeral service
as well?
Yes.
He that dwells under the shadow of the Almighty shall see, I'm blanking now, so lay on it.
But the body of the shelter, the God heaven, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, our English translation.
Yeah, there we go.
Yeah, so some 91.5 or 95, if you're looking at the Greek version, you will not fear the
the tear of the night, nor the arrow that flies by day.
And it's not nor the rush of the flies but...
It does say arrow there literally, but it's a reference to that.
Fresh of the the Bowman.
And if you go into the next verses, you get Debra, you get these other people who hang around with them all the time.
And the other things we've read.
And then probably the last time, not probably, the last time that we see,
We see Reshaff sort of in person as it were in the Bible.
book of Revelation in which he is one of the four horsemen of the apocalypse.
Yeah, we have to do a whole episode on that, I think at some point.
Yeah, so Revelation chapter six verse one, this is where you get the horsemen,
includes this line, and I looked and behold a white horse, and its rider had a bow,
and a crown was given to him, and he came out conquering and to conquer.
Right, so note the bow and this is the horseman who
generally called pestilence. Pestilence, right? You have war, famine, pestilence, and death,
right? Is the four horsemen of the apocalypse? This is pestilence. How is he getting identified
as pestilence? There's nothing about disease there. It's the bow. The bow, yeah. And Reshaf.
Right? And so this last image of the horsemen riding out as the seals are broken,
is of God.
judgment essentially unleashing everything, letting it go. And the character that
that gives to God's sort of final judgment at the end is that it's not that God
goes and does these horrible brutal things to people. It's that God stops
protecting them. There's been this period of time
This is another piece of biblical theodicy. There's been this period of time where God has been
protecting people and preserving people to give them time to repent. But eventually that time
for repentance comes to an end. And he lets things go. Right? And they go to their end. Right?
So it is in the context of the removal of protection, not God in flicking.
harmer violence. Right. Right. God's not throwing the arrows himself. He's letting this letting this force go. Yeah. And why is this force in the world because of human sin? Yeah.
So that's sort of this first stage where plague, disease, ill health, this is a force,
kind of with a name, right? It's a force, it's a demonic force in
in the world, then as we transition into the latter, or frankly to the period of exile
and afterward, and start moving toward the Second Temple period, we start getting examples
already in the Old Testament specifically with the Prophet's Elijah and Elijah of sort
of what we would think of as more traditional healings.
Yeah, so it kind of zooms in now on individual people.
And yeah, he's a racist being healed by other individual people. Yeah, oh my god through other individual people. Yeah, yeah, I mean a lie
General isha the big things about them are you know raising people from the dead
That's huge
That's you know
Were you three in the Bible we might think oh yeah a lot of people get raised from the dead but
No, that's huge someone comes back. Yeah
Yeah, yeah
Um, yeah.
So there's the raising of the widow's son raising the shoot of my woman's son by Alisha. So Alisha does it then Alisha does it right?
And then there's the healing of name in the leper by Alisha. Yeah go dip dip yourself in the muddy Jordan River
He complains aren't there much nicer rivers
Dip yourself in the river do you serious? Yeah, right?
Right, but so he's healed of his leprosy, right? So this is God healing a person
through the prayers the inner
session, right, through another person. And in these cases, right, so like the
leprosy that's afflicting Naibin is not personalized, right? There's not sort of
an exorcism that's done. And dipping yourself in the Jordan does not have the
character of an exorcism. No. As a character of cleansing or purification, right?
Even though it wasn't up to as standards in terms of water purity. Right? And
Edders
not sort of there's no mention, like there is say in Tobit. There's no mention that the
widow son of the Shunowite son, that some demon was involved somewhere. They're just
subject to these kinds of effects that are in the world.
And so this is really, this kind of healing is dealing with the effects of illness, disease,
the path, decay pestilence on the body of a person.
right on the person. Right. So to make a comparison, right, you look at, for example, we've talked
a couple times with a show about Korra's rebellion, right, when Korra stood up against Aaron and his
family who had been designated as high priests. Korra and his family were other Levites. They said,
aren't all the Israelites totally?
Are we all priests?
You know why are you putting on ears, right?
Um...
And not only does the ground swallow them up, but this plague breaks out in the camp.
Right, there's this outbreak of plague. People start dying. They go in the the priests go and Aaron goes
They take their sensors and they go and stand between the living and the dead and the plague is stopped
Right, that's very clearly a depiction of plague as this
Evil spiritual force, this demonic force. Yeah, right, that needs to be stopped by
priestly.
action. That's very different than what we see here with the healing of the person. There's a
direct parallel here to the way the Bible talks about sin. Especially the way St. Paul talks about sin.
As we've said many times on the show, most of the time, the vast majority of the time, when
And St. Paul talks about sin, it's in the singular.
He talks about sin not sins.
Right.
When he's talking about particular acts, he usually calls them transgressions or iniquities
or just translated it in different ways, right?
But he's referring to acts.
But when he talks about sin, so we have sin is this force in the world.
The way sin was crouching at Keynes door, right?
There's this force of sin that's at large in the world that needs to be wrestled with
and struggled with.
It's trying to master you.
You must master it, right?
at the same time.
Right? The scriptures do talk about, and even say Paul sometimes talk about, sins, the
individual actions committed by people and their consequences on those people, on their
relationships with other people. Right? Those are, those both exist in terms of sin and
those both exist in terms of sickness.
Right in terms of disease in terms of ailments, right? There is this demonic force out there of plague of
pestilence of disease right that is out there in the world
Right that has to be be put off that we we pray to God is priestly action. There are prayers, right?
And then there is the actual healing that has to happen with the individual person from the consequences of that
Right
And so the fact that these are so conceptually parallel, right, when we get to the gospels and we get to Christ's healings,
of course, all the people Christ's deals, there's too many to list, right? Even as long as we run this program, we could not run through every person Christ heals,
and not be here for at least until tomorrow.
But, right, one thing that you can notice, at least on several occasions.
Like Luke 517 through 26, Matthew 9 verses 1 through 8, Mark 2 verses 1 through 12, right?
Which all happened to be the healings of paralyzed people?
Yeah
One thing that you can notice is that Christ in his healings in those cases
explicitly
Connects the forgiveness of sins to the healing he's doing. Yeah
Let your sins be forgiven, take up your bed and walk.
Right, that these are, these are directly connected.
So sin and disease are really paralleled
in their biblical conceptions.
Right, sin has talked about like disease,
disease has talked about like sin, right?
They've talked about, these parallel ways, right?
So then, once again, questions potentially arise.
Are we f-?
failures. Just making for myself. No. Possibly confess your healing, father Steven.
See, my friend Michael Lansman has taught me how to speak this way. He's a bad influence.
So, right, so I at least am not a faith healer. I will let father Andrew answer for himself. I know I'm not.
But so why?
Right?
And what do we mean by?
we mean bye.
faith healer. We're not just using that as a pejorative, right?
Or talk about it and certain grifters of the 1990s.
And we also are not in this case, referring to like saints who
were we'll address this, but who like you people through prayer.
Right. Right. It's not what we're talking about. Right.
We're talking about the phenomenon in what would you say, primarily in
Pentecostal and charismatic circles, though not entirely, but primary.
Yeah, especially kind of the word faith,
penicostalism particularly.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And that's not limited to Protestantism, right?
There are other groups.
There are groups within Roman Catholicism.
There are other groups that are in that
penicostal charismatic mold.
Yep.
And plenty of Protestants who aren't, right?
But so that idea that you can sort of claim healing.
Right?
or that if you're belief
if your faith is strong enough, you will be healed.
Yeah.
Believe harder and boom.
And there's even this kind of thing
exists outside of Christianity, right?
Like the secret and all that stuff, right?
Like where that's taken to a weird pagan place, right?
Of sort of visualizing and declaring reality, right?
So, well, wait, if we're saying that sin and...
illness are so similar and so parallel. Why don't you that? Well, you can't do that with sins either.
Right. You can't just, I declare myself forgiven.
Yes. I claim this forgiveness. I declare victory over this temptation.
Yeah, which I mean, people do. Yeah, right. People say that stuff, but the truth is is that
repentance takes work. Yeah. And you have about the same track record I imagine of declaring
victory over addiction and declaring someone healed.
Right.
Probably not the same success rate.
Yeah.
You actually got to work at it.
You got to be reformed.
And I'm not saying you have to be reformed.
You've got to be reformed again.
Formed again.
That's right.
Yeah.
So receiving forgiveness, right, is it just like a declaration?
It requires repentance.
It requires work, right?
It's the recent repentance episode.
Right.
there
things you have to do, right? And in the same way, health, there are things you have to do.
That's how it normally works. Yes. That's you can't just declare yourself,
how do you can't just declare yourself forgiven? You can't, I mean, I've never seen one
in a shot. Just declare, declare weight loss. That would be a trick. I do that every morning.
You can see my track record. You can see my track record.
Right.
So, right.
But also, also, you can't just pray for it.
Right.
So we would say, right, that if you're diagnosed with something, or if you have a condition, or there's a health problem, right?
And you don't seek any kind of medical intervention, you just pray about it.
That is
exactly as problematic as I have sinned against someone and all I do is pray by
myself about it. Yeah like if I steal your car. Yeah God please forgive me. I'm
gonna keep the car but God please forgive me. Don't return the car, don't apologize,
don't try to just you know just pray about it and feel better right. Again
that's not how either of those work.
So then, right, why do we pray? Well, we're going to get more into that. Why do we pray for healing?
Right? Because saying don't just do it doesn't mean don't do it at all. Right?
That's right. But that's because God works through means.
Yeah. Right? God heals a lot of people through medications and through doctors.
Right. Because ultimately, he provided all that stuff.
he provided, you know, the doctor's ability.
gain that knowledge. He provided the raw material, like you provided, you know, every
yes. And he forgives in the sense of healing and restoring a lot of sin, right? Through
kind words, shared meals. Yeah. And even repentance is described as being a gift from God.
It doesn't mean he zaps you and says, bam, now you're repenting. It's, okay, here's how
you repent. Here's all the means you need. And it's going to work because I'm giving this
to you. Yeah.
You gotta use it.
Yes.
So it's not something you're entitled to, forgiveness is not something you're entitled
to that you can claim, and bodily health is not something you're entitled to that you
can claim.
Sorry word-faced preachers.
Folk at all.
Exactly.
All right, well, we're gonna go ahead and take our second break for this episode on
Unction here in the Lord of Spirits and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
the complete life and teachings of our Lord, from before his conception in Mary's womb
until his ascension. Revealed 20th-century Egyptian elder and scholar Matthew the poor,
wrote many volumes on the subject of Christ's significance, life, and teachings.
Which translator James Helmi has distilled into one highly readable book that will make
a valuable addition to every Christian's library.
The story of Jesus is now available in paper...
back and ebook at store.angianfake.com.
That's store.angianfake.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
You know, I'm wondering if this has the most
Sorry whoever.
of any episode of Lord of Spirits. I mean you do throw a lot of sorry's in
whole Council of God. Yes. This is I think the apology episode really.
Or the most Canadian episode. One of the two. That's you know story
Calvinists. Yeah. He might be an ex-man. Yeah. It's not good. Well that
we've alienated them. Story Canadian. I do have to say with that
word. That sounds like a wonderful book. I have not read it yet. So I'm
I'm not being critical of.
book. But my issue with the commercial is that anytime I hear part blank, part
blank, my brain fills in all cop. Wow, I never never thought that I would hear
the confluence of Robocop with an Egyptian. Yes, like anything. Anything.
Art German Shepherd, part Poodle, all cop. Oh, it doesn't matter. That's where my
brain goes. Nice. It's just...
a wording thing.
I understood.
Well, I'll send that note to our marketing department.
Pass that on for me, if you would.
Well, they all listen to the show.
So, you know, they love my advice, I know.
And we need every last syllable of it.
So all right, well, for those of you who have your generic Lord of Spirits episode scripts
out, you know that the third half is always the one we begin talking about the thing that
was actually about. And I also think, because I knew I had to throw this out there. If anyone ever creates the Lord of
Spirits wiki, Lord of Spirits wiki, that probably the generic show outline is going to be one of the articles.
So it should be. It should be. I mean, think of the amount of material that's there.
Right. Just like song references. Exactly. Exactly. In jokes, I mean, there could be all kinds of wiki pages out
their people. So you know.
Just saying I think most of our audience though are people with long commutes
That's true. They're not going to be doing all they live themselves to wiki editing. I think that's your law in the
Although once we have self-driving cars watch there. We go. There's be a proliferation of wikis
There we go. I have a brisket self-driving car, but it's scary. Oh neat
Well, we're testing out of here's the thing you're not thinking about
So the self-driving cars have an ethical algorithm.
Yes, right.
Right?
To what to do, you know, pedestrian jumps out.
What do you do?
Yeah, do you save the pedestrian or do you save the drive?
There are a certain set of scenarios in which your car will choose to kill you rather
than someone else or someone else's.
Yeah.
So before you buy a self-driving car, be aware of that.
will go out.
thousand on you given the right circumstance.
You know, most of us not going to buy self driving cars.
Most of us is going to order them on our apps.
They'll just show up at your house, pick you up,
take you where you want to go.
My strategy is to drive like a 25 year old car.
And instead of replacing the car,
you just replace one part at a time.
Oh, the car of Thesius.
Yes, it's the Johnny Cash method of new car purchase.
purchase. I thought about Johnny
earlier when I was reading that bit from the apocalypse because I always whenever I read the book of
Revelation I hear it in the voice of Johnny Cash. Yeah well you can hear him read it on YouTube. Yes I
know. I know. This is that banter again that all the things just cut this part of the transcript.
Okay, skip, skip, skip, skip.
So, okay, well, now we're actually gonna talk
about those sacramid.
say, but of course all this stuff we talked about goes into this. You can't just listen to the third half.
There's there's yeah. So yeah, so so you know kind of ground zero as it were of scriptural references
for this is what someone asked you holy yonction. Where's that in the Bible? Where's that in the Bible?
It's literally explicitly commanded in the Bible. Yes. Yeah, so I don't know why a lot of people
they'll do this. We do it. So James chapter 5 verses 14 and 15, is anyone among...
you sick. Let him call for the presbyterers of the church and let them pray over him, anointing
him with oil in the name of the Lord, and the prayer of faith will save the one who is sick,
as the Lord will raise him up. And if he has committed sins, he will be forgiven."
So note that connection between forgiveness of sins and healing of sickness.
Yes. Right there together in one sacrament.
They're right there. And so this is why we had to go through that other stuff before we got here.
Right. How are they? Right.
And so why is this a sacrament or why is this a mystery of the church? Well, like the others, this is God working through created material means.
Yes.
It's oil and its presbyters and their hands and their prayer.
And it's a Bible.
God, who does it? God will raise them up.
Right. God doing it through. Right.
Just like as we saw right with baptism you've got water
You've got meron, you've got mer oil, right?
Marriage, you have a man and a woman, right?
You have these material that are, right,
how the mystery works, and here you have oil, right?
Yep. God working through the oil.
And for folks who aren't orthodox or maybe haven't been
haven't been to an function service because not all
Orthodox churches do this regularly.
Yeah.
The, the, several of the details in here are followed in the way we do it in the Orthodox
church.
Like you'll know that it says, presbyter's plural ideally, the function services served by
seven presbyter, seven priests.
Yeah.
And the way that gets, one of the ways that gets expressed within the services that there's
seven gospels and traditionally seven anointings.
although the way that it's usually done with lots of people,
once is one anointing at the end.
But yeah.
Yeah, and so the people are prayed over as it says.
And there is actually at one point
where they are blessed with the gospel book.
Yeah.
The Bible itself and the prayer speaks of God's healing hand,
which is present in that gospel.
Yeah.
Very powerful.
So to give you sort of more of an idea, right, of how we do it.
And that's what we do the big service.
Oil from that service is also capped.
And so the, you know, in situations where someone's in the hospital,
someone's sick, right?
The, the, the pressman or the priest can go and annoy them, right?
You don't need to gather up seven, seven priests and do the whole service
every time someone needs to be anointed.
That's usually done.
when you're doing it for the whole congregation, the whole.
Right. I mean, that's theoretically the ideal
is that you would do that whole thing every time, but it's not generally practical.
But yeah.
So, here again, this is what Andrew mentioned. You see
the forgiveness of sins and healing sort of
itextricably linked.
together, right? And even though they're linked and we talked about in the last half, how we see that
in Christ's healings, how they're linked, then we talked a little bit about how they're related
in being parallel to each other. There are still a lot of ways in which those two dots get connected
that are really bad.
And the reason I say they're really bad is not just, oh, that is...
correct theology, you use the incorrect preposition. You are a heretic sir on the internet, right?
They're wrong and they're bad because of the consequences they have for people.
Yeah. And especially in this area of healing, the idea of miraculous healing,
people have done horrible harm and damage.
Oh yeah. By misunderstanding this. Yeah.
Literally people have died without men.
medical treatment because of these wrong theological
understanding.
Right.
Or had their faith destroyed, you know, their faith in Christ
because like, well, you just, your faith is too weak
and that's why you're still suffering, you know.
Yes.
Yeah.
So people have been victimized in any number of ways,
but that's why we're saying these are really bad, right?
Yeah.
So the first of those, you know, the book of Joe being
exhibited is that there's a causative relationship between
sin and suffering or illness.
Right. Yeah, you did something bad and so therefore you are sick or suffering. Right. You've got
in your life. Yes, you're being punished. God is smacking you down because the bad thing you did.
Yes. And and relatively few, not no one unfortunately, but relatively few people would say it that
explicitly, but a lot of people think it. Right. It's in there at a certain level. Right. Yeah.
Why is that person or that family suffering so much? Oh, they'll be bad.
What's the...
something going on, there must be something wrong.
Right.
Another really bad one is that sin or illness or hey, the world is kind of illusory.
It isn't real.
And this is sorry Mary Baker Eddie for the first time.
If I don't, boom.
In almost three years of podcasting together, finally get to say sorry Mary Baker Eddie.
I don't know if we have any Christian science people that listen to this so, but if we do,
I wanna hear from you.
I just want to know that you're out there and say, welcome for science and health with
key to the scriptures.
I say the name.
Yeah.
Oh, and my favorite.
Okay.
So I just have to throw this out there for those of you who have not read a certain
little book called orthodoxy and heterodoxy.
One of my favorite.
There's a series of sermon, sermon lessons that they read from Mary Baker and he's
stuff and one of them is called something like
is the world and everything in
the result of atomic force. I think that's what it is. But I mean, it's this idea, right?
That everything is just the function of mind. So sickness is because you're thinking bad.
Yes, which is what sin is within that system. Yeah, right. It's sort of this delusion. And it's
sort of, if you look at her influences, man, I'm really trash in the Christian side. I was much
much nicer to the Mormons.
But if you look at our info...
influences, it's a bunch of half-rate quasi-Hindu grifters in the early 20th century.
People who set themselves up as quote unquote swamis and stuff.
I mean, that whole sort of new thought movement is, I'm sorry, it's really wacky.
It's actually, it's interesting, you can trace it down into the mid-20th century word faith
like there's this there's a line that you can trace pretty easily between that
in the 19th century and then this other stuff.
So yeah.
And again, the reason I'm going harder on this is how destructive it is.
Right.
People refusing to give their children medical care.
This is serious stuff at this point.
Yeah.
Faith harder and everything will be fine.
This isn't just like, you know, you added the phileocate of the creed, right, which is
bad enough.
Sorry Roman Catholic friends.
But who else is the other part?
I apologize to this. This is a whole I didn't think they would the whole other level of destructive this right thought this would be an inocuous
Anxious episode. Yes. Yes. It has not been so anxious after all.
Yes. Yes. Yes. So that sense that the world and of course sickness is illusory. That's kind of the second in our Rogues gallery.
Yeah of uh of errors it is as my father once pointed out.
to me. He had never been inside a Christian science reading room where everyone wasn't wearing glasses.
Ha, so take that as you will.
That one for later, that's good.
Yeah, that's so, but probably the most common one, right? Because I don't know that we had any
Christian scientist or Church of Religious Science folks for me to run off just now
And as I said, not a lot of people would verbalize that, oh yes, if you get sick, it's because
you sinned, right?
They wouldn't have these verbalized it that way.
This third one is held by just about everybody who's an American.
And usually unconsciously.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, often consciously, but usually unconsciously.
Yeah.
That's that there are these
partitioned sort of separate spheres.
There's sort of physical health,
which is this science-based thing,
of biochemistry, et cetera, et cetera.
There's mental health.
There may be crossover between these things.
There's mental health which may also be
reducible to biochemistry or may not,
depending on your point of view.
Yeah. But that's a separate thing.
Yeah.
There's spiritual health or issues of sin,
which are this third.
separate other thing. And that ultimately they don't connect. And in a lot of
cases this is a reaction to especially the first bad view. Right. So they would
don't want to say they're horrified by someone saying, oh you got sick because you
sinned. And so they say look no sin and physical health have nothing to do with
each other. Yeah look it's just an illness you know this is not your fault. Right
and see what's going to happen.
Sin is this legal thing of sin and forgiveness.
Mental health is this other thing that we address through psychoanalysis or psychotherapy.
And then physical health is this sort of other thing.
And so the problem with this is even though a lot of people, if not most Americans,
ask we'll say yes these are these separate spheres.
Functionally, we all know that they overlap all the time.
Yeah, because you're having one kind of experience.
Yes.
All at once.
You know, the wretchedness that you feel in the midst of having COVID for the eighth time
or whatever, is not...
You can't just say, well, my body's kind of feeling like crap, but I'm good.
Like, you might say that to yourself, but that is not how you feel.
It's not that you really are being
And like, you know, to try to work that's out of my head,
the sort of thought experiment that worked for me was
saints suffering from disease, right?
So a saint is a very holy person.
You would certainly never say about them
while they're suffering a disease
because of their sins, because of their bad sins.
You wouldn't say that.
And certainly, you know, we're not gonna say it's an illusion.
But we might be tempted to say, well, you know, there
souls in great shape, but their body, you know, or God has allowed this to happen to them,
you know, whatever, right? But they are not partitioned out because they're still embodied
humans. So a saint might well feel while they have maybe some major element, they might
feel depression. They might feel the sense of spiritual struggle. Those things are going
Go
along with it. That doesn't mean there any less holy. Yeah, you know, it's still a physical
spiritual embodied soulful all at once thing, you know, it's all together. It's one. Yeah.
If you're living with chronic pain, you're going to experience periods of depression. Yeah.
Especially during those periods of depression, it's going to be hard to pray, right? Or maybe
anger, which is I mean, anger is a spiritual experience too. Yeah. You know, it's all those things
together. You know.
It's a spiritual and physical and physical.
You feel hot.
You feel energized when you're angry.
You know?
Yeah.
And you're going to, if you're dealing with crippling anxiety and stress, right?
That's going to have physical consequences to your physical body.
That's going to do damage your physical body.
That's going to make it again very difficult to pray.
It's going to make it very difficult to focus.
It's gonna make it very difficult to find time to do it.
to live the Christian life the way you know you should, right?
There's not a causative relationship here, right?
And all of this is real.
None of it is illusory.
Yeah, and also it all overlaps.
You're a whole person.
Exactly.
And I mean, I think one of the reasons
why people try to separate it out
is because they're looking for solutions.
Right?
So like, well, look, you've got a headache.
Just take the pill.
you know but
which okay, you take a pill, you might well feel better. It's true. But the experience is more
than just a pain in your head. It's also all these other things at the same time as we said. So
shouldn't you also be praying? Shouldn't you also be maybe dealing with, like your headache might
well be connected to other things going on in your life, you know, shouldn't you also deal with them,
you know, all those things together. Like if you just constantly treat the symptom,
then you might not be dealing with
the overall true disease, right?
And healing brought to one part of that, right?
So certain people can only address certain parts of that.
Yeah.
So your local family doctor cannot address the spiritual part.
Right.
Probably an eye is a priest cannot address the physical part.
That's not your deal.
Right.
Like if you've got low grade kidney failure, right?
You need to go to a doctor, not to me, right?
while you're getting the tree.
for kidney failure, I will come and talk to you and hear your confession.
Right.
I'll annoy you with oil.
Are you saying people that Cajun food might have kidney failure issues?
Or I don't know.
I don't know.
Dehydration for all the sweating we do in August.
But I mean, it should be emphasized, right, that what you can do for that person and what
the kidney doctor does for that person are all from, are both from God.
Both of those things are from God and are both things they need.
Right.
Right? Just...
getting your physical health in order,
if your mental, your spiritual health
or out of whack isn't gonna do a lot of good for you
because it's gonna start failing too
because these things overlap.
And vice versa, right?
When you're struggling with mental illness
or physical illness,
as that starts to be alleviated,
that struggle starts to be alleviated
and you get help with those things,
one of the things that does is, for example,
open up space for repentance,
Hmm. For going and making a man.
for going and dealing with things that you know you need to deal with as a Christian,
but that you couldn't because of the other things that we're going on.
So these things all go together. Not only does the suffering overlap and relate, but
the healing is holistic and the healing overlaps.
And so what we're talking about when we're talking about healing in this full
sense, the kind of healing that we're praying for when we perform the anointing of the sick.
Right? This is the restoration of the whole human person. So that includes your biological life,
includes your spiritual life, the life of the soul, right, which is the life of the body.
It includes the health of the relationships, right, that you have with the world around you,
Right? The people around you. It includes the restoration of
of your identity, because your identity is formed out of those relationships and those
interactions and those roles you play, right, society. All of that is restored as you are
healed. And so it's not just like, oh, my body is healed, my soul is healed, my mind is
right? You are healed. Yeah. The you the
you are is what's healed. Right. So while that said, right,
obviously, you know, there are a whole lot of people who
receive the anointing of the sick. And not only aren't healed
immediately, sometimes aren't healed at all, sometimes it's
someone who's approaching physical death. And even though they
receive the anointing of the sick, they still die. Right. Oh,
So I
that, right? Does God, because I'd not want to hear heal people? Is there some stuff
he can't heal? Is there something they did wrong to not receive the healing? Right? Well,
we've already ruled that last one out, right? Yeah. Well, and just like it's our practice
generally to annoy people when we full well believe that they're dying. Yes. Yeah. Yeah.
Is that like you Hail Mary pass, whatever? Yeah. We don't do last, in the Orthodox church,
We don't do last row.
writes per se for a row of Catholic friends.
We do the anointing at various points,
but that includes what's on their deathbed.
We will go and give them the anointing of the sick.
Right.
So our our function is less extreme.
You know what it's mean.
Um, nice.
But, um, so why, why is this?
Well, you remember, and we've talked about this,
I know several times on the show,
all the way back in Genesis chapter three,
It is
not good for man to live forever in this state.
Oh yeah, that. And it still isn't.
Yeah, it still isn't. Right.
St. Paul was still able to say, you know, it's better for me to depart
this life, but it's better for you if I stay.
Right. Um,
And so...
It is not aimed at the sacrament of function that God's healing in general is not aimed at keeping humans alive forever in this world.
Lazarus died again later.
Yeah, I mean everybody who got raised died again later.
All the people who Jesus healed died eventually.
Right. Yeah. But the healing we were
even this life, the restoration we receive in this life gives us more time to repent.
Gives us more time in this world to serve the purpose of our life in this world, which is repentance,
which is transformation. But there's a point at which that is done.
Where the repentance we need to do is done or we've run out of chances.
You don't want to raise us to us, or chances, but on the positive side that what God required
of us in terms of repentance, in terms of the good works he's given us to do in this world,
et cetera, that's done.
And then it is time for us for our life in this world to end.
And that is because the ultimate, the final restoration of the human person and our identity
We're...
we really become who we are, right, is in the bodily resurrection. That's what this
is aimed at. So the healing we receive now is sort of a temporary measure, it's sort
of a foretaste, right? It's a gift, it's a blessing, it's a little bit of an extension
of our lives here to allow us to do what we need to do, right? But it's not a substitute,
definitely not a way to try to avoid us moving on through death.
as Christ died to our bodily resurrection as he was raised from the dead.
Yeah. It's an anticipation of it, not a staving off of it.
So, as we wrap up, the first thing I want to say is,
I can't believe we're actually right at this moment under two hours.
How about that? Maybe it's because we extracted a lot of giggling.
that we would have otherwise included, I don't know.
But, Ani, on a much more serious note,
there's a couple of things I want to leave everybody with.
So one is,
if you've ever been at a Holy Unction Service
that I've served, you know,
especially during the years that I was doing
pastoral ministry still,
and I preached afterwards, which I did once in a while,
I would often raise one question
with
which is, okay, we're all coming in here for this healing sacrament.
Why is it that everybody is not walking out, miraculous, secured of whatever they walked
in here with?
Right.
And that's even aside from the fact that most people who come into the function service
are probably relatively well and soul and relatively well and body anyway.
But you know, especially as you get past middle age, you got something that hurts, probably,
on that's uncomfortable on a regular basis.
Why doesn't Holy Unction just make that go away?
I mean, if you listen up to this point,
you probably know the answer to that, which is,
it's not that this is some kind of head-fake on God's part.
Like, yeah, yeah, this is the healing sacrament,
but suckers, you know, most of you are not going to get healed most of the time.
That's not it at all.
This sacrament is for the healing of soul and
body and it's not like, well, okay, well, we got the soul in even though the body isn't
really going for anything at this point.
No, that's not it at all because as we started out, what, who is a human?
You are a body.
You are an end-sold body and an in live and animated body.
It's who you are.
And so the sacrament affects your body in all of the
senses that that means, not just in terms of the materiality that we tend to think about when we think about the body, although including that for sure, but also, you know, frankly, see our body episodes, all of your powers, your potentialities, all those things together.
So is it not working? It is. It is. But whereas it's aiming. And the whole point of it is the resurrected person.
It's aiming towards the resurrection and how do you how are you resurrected with the resurrection of life rather than the resurrection of
Dhamnation you raise the resurrection of life by faithfulness to Christ
By holding fast to him by always coming back to him and
That's what function is for it aims at that at enabling you to do that in this life so that
that in the resurrection.
you are who you're supposed to be in your fullness.
The second thing I wanted to mention and that's related to the first for sure, is a lot
more personal, but I know it's not exclusive to me because I know that probably a lot of
you listening out there have experienced this.
So if you're married, there's a good chance that you and your spouse have experienced
miscarriage. Statistically, it's a really good chance. And that's a difficult thing to experience.
My wife and I have experienced that. And there's so many feelings that go along with that, right?
It's not just a sense of a loss of potential, like you know, you're coming up with baby names,
you're maybe outfitting a room, you're telling your other kids if you've got them.
It's not just that, but there's also a sense of not quite knowing what to do with a person
who died but was never really present to you in the most palpable way.
You know, certainly mom feels the presence of that child in ways that nobody else does, but
and she's the one who suffers the most.
And there's a lot of things.
things you can do to heal from that suffering.
But that's not the thing that I want to talk about.
Rather, I want to pass on to you something that was passed on to me that had obviously
been passed on before.
And one of these experiences that we had, I was actually away from my wife at the time.
We were not in the same part of the country.
And it was tough.
very tough for that to be the, I mean, you know, we couldn't have planned for that. And so
I was, I was actually at an event with a number of other clergy and I ran into one of our,
one of our bishops and I'll just go ahead and say who it was because I'm grateful that he
did for this. It was Bishop John. So if you're in the adieu can I assist you might know Bishop John.
And he says to me, how are you doing? And it wasn't just casual, you know, you ever talked to him,
He's a good...
pastor kind of all the time. And you know, I know him. I've known him for years. And so I told him,
I told him what had happened. And he passed this on to me. He said, you know, I've ever heard what
Father Thomas Hopko used to say about this situation. I said, you know what, I have not. And he said,
and now I'm not passing this on to you to tell you that this is some kind of dogmatic teaching,
but it's something that I believe is true. Okay, that's where I'm going to put it. He said this,
God gives a
Everything that they need in order to be saved.
Everyone in this world, God gives them everything that they need.
Everything in your life is there for you, for your salvation.
And if you use it, you'll be saved.
You have what you need.
And what Father Thomas Hopko would say is that when God
takes someone like this in this situation, a situation of miscarriage,
It's because that...
person already has, they're already fit. They're already ready to go. And so it's
their moment. God is already receiving them. Again, I'm not saying this is some kind of
dogmatic teaching. If you don't believe this, you're not Christian or not Orthodox,
whatever. But I think that this aims at a lot of what we're talking about, that the
ultimate goal for us as
creations of God is to be with Him, is to be fit to be with Him, to be prepared to be with Him.
And that's what function is aimed at. That's what function is for. Just because we don't walk
away with miracle cures doesn't mean it's not working. This is with any of the other sacraments.
Just because you don't walk away glowing or whatever doesn't mean it's not working. It's making
Making you more and more...
fit for the kingdom of God more and more fit ultimately for the resurrection, for this embodied
whole humanity cured of corruption with God forever. That's what it's for.
Father Stephen. You do need to speak for yourself a little bit. I am positively radiant
nearly all the time. That is the adjective I think that...
best describes me in most people's minds. So earlier when we were talking, I made a reference to
essence not preceding existence, right, that who you are does not precede the life you live,
and are more philosophically inclined or francophilic listeners may have caught a...
sort of reference to Jean-Paul Sartre and his famous among nerds, axiom that existence
precedes essence. And by that he meant that we sort of come into being and we aren't
anything in particular. And as we make choices in our life, those choices define who we are.
And he used the example.
at one point of how you can compose your life like a melody through the choices you make.
And you know, I mean, that sounds nice, but it's the opposite extreme.
Right, it's the opposite extreme. So on one side, you have those who would tell us that, you know,
know before you're even born right you are x you will always be x.
X is just going to play out over your life. On the other side, you have people who
like John Paul Sartre who are so obsessed with the idea of ultimate freedom that they're
not willing to acknowledge that you're born in a particular place in a particular time
in a particular body with particular genetics, in a particular heritage. You speak a particular
language and that shapes how you think about things and how you see the world and you
have particular experience.
experiences early in life that aren't subject to your control, right?
You want us to ignore all of that, right?
And in between, we have one of the truths we're kind of trying to get at in this episode,
coming back to what Father Staneloise said about a human person being in some sense absolute.
because that quality
that God has given to us, that he's built into our Constitution.
Of being able to step outside of, to evaluate,
and I won't go down this rabbit hole now, but you can go back to the episode,
this is really a function of the news, of reason in the truest sense.
to look at our lives, to like the prodigal son come to our senses.
that is something that we possess as a capacity, as part of our human nature, at every moment of our lives.
Not just at the first moment, or at the early moments, but until the very last moment when we draw our last breath.
Meaning, no matter how.
how you've spent the last
umpteen years, no matter who
you've been, no matter how
distorted that is, no matter
how much guilt that's heaped upon
you, no matter how much you've
hurt yourself and other people,
no matter how much damage you've
done, no matter what people
think of you, no matter what
you think of yourself, that
can all change.
You
You can break character.
You don't have to keep playing the part you've been playing.
You don't have to keep operating within the relationships and the patterns that you've
been operating in.
But that's also not, again, contra at least one reading of Sart, not something you do by
snapping your fingers.
That's not something you can declare.
It's not something you can wake up day at one day and just say, okay, done with all that,
I'm going to have a whole...
new person now. It starts there and then it takes a lot of work. The work of
repentance, the work of making new choices, the work of repairing damage
relationships, of repairing loss of respect, from other people and for yourself.
The work of making peace where you've been making conflict and trying to win.
the work of
being healed as a whole and complete person in every way,
transforming yourself, transforming your life.
Because again, identity is not found back before our birth.
It's not found at our birth. It's not found at some high point in our life age 30,
age 40.
Right, it's found at the point.
point of the bodily resurrection. That is the point in our life and our existence
where we most truly will be who we are. And until then, we are actively shaping that,
actively transforming that. And free not to pivot on a dime, free not from the consequences
So
our past actions, as if they can just be brushed aside, but free to begin the work of becoming
that person who we want to be on that day instead of the person who we may have been.
Amen.
Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you very much for listening everyone.
If you didn't get through to a slide, we would still love to hear from you.
You can email us at Lordofspiritsatintenfath.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page or you can leave us a voicemail at SpeakPipe.com
slash Lordofspirits.
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at
7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific.
Then I put my codes in the machine that the world I found was made of faulty dreams.
If you are on Facebook, that dark, dark place, but not as dark as Twitter.
Follow our page and join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings everywhere, but
most importantly, share this show with a friend who is going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.anxiofaith.com.stokesupport and help make sure we and lots of
other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Fly out of the doldrums and recall the log from the early database of your loan.
Thank you, good night and may God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round
about the throne, and the beasts, and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times
10,000, and thousands of thousands, seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land that
was slain to receive power, and riches, and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory,
and blessing.
Revelation, Chapter 5, verses 11-12.